<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PHP on Clint Berry</title>
    <link>https://clintberry.com/categories/php/</link>
    <description>Recent content in PHP on Clint Berry</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://clintberry.com/categories/php/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Backbone.js apps with Authentication Tutorial</title>
      <link>https://clintberry.com/2012/backbone-js-apps-authentication-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://clintberry.com/2012/backbone-js-apps-authentication-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://clintberry.com/images/backbonelocked.png&#34; alt=&#34;backbonelocked&#34; title=&#34;backbonelocked&#34; width=&#34;568&#34; height=&#34;111&#34; class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-670&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my current company I am working on my first large-scale production backbone.js app and I couldn&amp;#8217;t be happier. After using backbone.js for a few months I have caught the vision and I am becoming more and more proficient. But every once and a while I still run into problems I would consider basic, but I can&amp;#8217;t seem to find much help on the interwebs. Authentication with backbone.js apps was one of those problems. So I am posting the solution I came up with in hopes it will benefit someone else, and hopefully will garner some feedback or potentially better ways to solve authentication with Backbone.js.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phing For PHP Deployment</title>
      <link>https://clintberry.com/2012/phing-php-deployment/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://clintberry.com/2012/phing-php-deployment/</guid>
      <description>I recently did a presentation at the Utah PHP Users group on Phing for deploying PHP applications. Here are the slides:
http://clintberry.com/slides/phing</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sublime Text 2 for PHP &amp; WordPress Development</title>
      <link>https://clintberry.com/2012/sublime-text-2-php-symfony-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://clintberry.com/2012/sublime-text-2-php-symfony-development/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sublime Text 2 is an amazing code editor that I started using on the recommendation of a friend. I fell in love and haven&amp;#8217;t looked back. Here are some recomendations for setting up Sublime Text 2 for PHP and WordPress development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Custom User Providers in Symfony2</title>
      <link>https://clintberry.com/2011/custom-user-providers-symfony2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://clintberry.com/2011/custom-user-providers-symfony2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;why-custom-user-providers&#34;&gt;Why Custom User Providers?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my current job all the database systems are managed by DB admins and the developers have to connect to the database via web services. We do not connect to the databases directly. This allows for better &lt;a title=&#34;Separation of Concerns&#34; href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Separation_of_concerns&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;separation of concerns&lt;/a&gt; and allows experts to focus on their respective specialties. But if you are programming a Symfony2 app, that means you don&amp;#8217;t get to use Doctrine or any other ORM, which in turn means you create your own models/entities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you want to develop the authentication parts of your new app you will quickly find that there is plenty of documentation for Doctrine/ORM based apps, but if you are using your own custom models then you run into pages &lt;del datetime=&#34;2012-01-20T21:30:13+00:00&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://symfony.com/doc/current/cookbook/security/custom_provider.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;like this one&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/del&gt;.  &lt;del datetime=&#34;2012-01-20T21:30:13+00:00&#34;&gt;(when I finish this post I will submit an article to the docs and see if they approve it)&lt;/del&gt; &lt;strong&gt;UPDATE: Someone beat me to it, there is now a good tutorial in the Symfony docs for custom user providers.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Switched to Symfony 2 Framework</title>
      <link>https://clintberry.com/2011/switched-symfony-2-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://clintberry.com/2011/switched-symfony-2-framework/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been working with the Zend Framework for the last 3 years. I like it. It is flexible, heavily object oriented, and organized. However, one thing that has always bothered me is that modules in ZF have been &lt;a title=&#34;Zend Framework Modules&#34; href=&#34;http://weierophinney.net/matthew/archives/234-Module-Bootstraps-in-Zend-Framework-Dos-and-Donts.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;second-class citizens&lt;/a&gt;. Granted, in Zend Framework 2 this is not the case, but I needed to start a project right away, and since ZF2 is still in beta, I decided to go checkout some other frameworks again.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speed Up Your WordPress Development Cycle With Git</title>
      <link>https://clintberry.com/2011/speed-up-your-wordpress-development-cycle-with-git/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://clintberry.com/2011/speed-up-your-wordpress-development-cycle-with-git/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you have developed WordPress sites for clients this process might sound familiar to you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a new client that wants a wordpress site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the most recent wordpress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find a good current blank wordpress theme to start implementing the design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upload to a staging server to for client to see&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Client requests changes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You make changes on local server, then upload to staging server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat last three steps until finished and then you deploy the site to live&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After lots of trial and error, I have come up with a process that is more efficient, and allows rapid development of wordpress sites. I use Git, Git Submodules, and WordPress child themes to get going quicker and keep code up to date with minimal effort. (If your not using a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revision_control&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;revision control &lt;/a&gt;system like &lt;a href=&#34;http://git-scm.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://subversion.tigris.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SVN&lt;/a&gt; for development, then check out &lt;del datetime=&#34;2012-04-22T20:33:39+00:00&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/132520/good-excuses-not-to-use-version-control&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this funny question and answer session on Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/del&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; Stack Overflow moderators removed the question&amp;#8230; bummer. Check out the funny-ness in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.archive.org/web/20100722082534/http://stackoverflow.com/questions/132520/good-excuses-not-to-use-version-control&#34; title=&#34;Why to use version control&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;wayback machine internet archiver&lt;/a&gt; instead)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>