<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Clint Berry</title>
    <link>https://clintberry.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Clint Berry</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://clintberry.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Engineering Compensation - The Pursuit of Fairness</title>
      <link>https://clintberry.com/engineering-compensation-fair/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://clintberry.com/engineering-compensation-fair/</guid>
      <description>In the product development department at Weave, our motto is Never Satisfied. We are constantly trying to improve how we work, including experimenting with changes to department processes and organization as a whole.
One of the ways we have improved over the last couple of years is how we determine engineering compensation. Historically it has been hard to determine pay structure and ultimately those who could negotiate best had an advantage.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What does a CTO do?</title>
      <link>https://clintberry.com/what-does-a-cto-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://clintberry.com/what-does-a-cto-do/</guid>
      <description>I get asked this question a lot: What does a CTO do? As a &amp;ldquo;rookie CTO&amp;rdquo; and co-founder of a software company, I even have to ask myself that question from time to time, especially as the company has grown and I have had to adapt. So I have spent some time researching the role, and interviewing several CTOs to get an idea of their responsibilities and day-to-day workflow. Here is what I have found:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://clintberry.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://clintberry.com/about/</guid>
      <description>I am the co-founder and CTO of Weave and a winter 2014 Y-combinator alumni.
Passions  I love my wife I love my children I love wakeboarding I love snow skiing I love reading I love ping-pong (if I don&amp;rsquo;t call it table tennis it doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I suck) I love start-up companies I love open source I love real-time communication  A Brief Timeline of my Early Technical History 1988 &amp;#8211; I am 6 years old and my mother gets a home computer from her employer (JCPenney).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://clintberry.com/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://clintberry.com/contact/</guid>
      <description>Twitter Follow @clinton_berry
LinkedIn http://www.linkedin.com/in/clintonberry
Email clint@system-11.com</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>