<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About-2s on Clint Berry</title>
    <link>http://clintberry.github.io/about-2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in About-2s on Clint Berry</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://clintberry.github.io/about-2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>http://clintberry.github.io/about-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://clintberry.github.io/about-2/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://clintberry.com/images/profile_photo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;profile_photo&#34; width=&#34;128&#34; height=&#34;132&#34; class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-656&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a web developer and wannabe entrepreneur. I love working with small businesses and showing them how web-based software can help with their business processes. I am passionate about e-commerce and real-time web applications. I am familiar with SEO and website conversion optimization. Here are some of my specialties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Server Side: Node.js, PHP, Zend Framework, Python, WordPress&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Front-end: Angular, Backbone, JQuery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Databases: MySQL, MongoDB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sysadmin: Linux (Ubuntu, CentOS)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other: Magento, FreeSWITCH, AppJS, Node-webkit, PhoneGap&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the things I love (in no particular order, except the first):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love my wife&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love wakeboarding&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love snow skiing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love reading&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love ping-pong (if I don&amp;#8217;t call it table tennis it doesn&amp;#8217;t mean I suck)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love start-up companies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love e-commerce&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to &lt;a href=&#34;http://clintberry.github.io/contact/&#34;&gt;contact me&lt;/a&gt; with any questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-brief-timeline-of-my-technical-history:d680e8a854a7cbad6d490c445cba2eba&#34;&gt;A Brief Timeline of my Technical History&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1988&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8211; I am 6 years old and my mother gets a home computer from her employer (JCPenney). I am hooked. I play Pitfall and mess around with DOS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1992&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8211; My family gets a new Compaq 386 computer with Windows 3.0. I am blown away. I am introduced to QBasic by a neighbor and start programming for the first time. I am shocked I can make this awesome machine do things by simply giving it commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1995&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8211; My family gets another computer upgrade, a Packard Bell bundled Windows 95. We get access to the internet via modem. Webcrawler is my search engine of choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1996&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8211; I create my first GeoCities account and start learning HTML. I am enthralled with the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1998&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8211; In 9th grade a friend and I post a website for our school where students can print hall passes and view curriculums from classes. Teachers are upset, but no disciplinary action taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2000&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8211; Two friends and I enter an educational website competition and we each win $100. We build the site with PHP. I still haven&amp;#8217;t grasped that web development will be my future career. I spend hours trying to do my first Red Hat linux installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2001&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8211; A friend and I break into the school network. We don&amp;#8217;t change any grades, but we do have a little fun (transferring students we didn&amp;#8217;t like to ridiculous classes). We get busted and suspended for 5 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2004&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8211; I start college at Utah Valley University and play on the lacrosse team. I have a job at Kinkos and I take my first class on linux and start c++ classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2005&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8211; I quit Kinkos and start work for Avinti building a web-based dashboard for viewing email anti-virus data (PHP). It is my first time getting paid for programming and I love it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2006&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8211; I land my first independent software contract for a web-based sales tracking software. The company uses it for 3 years and I sell all the rights to the software. I realize that my passion lies in web-based software, especially software-as-a-service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/116690395418514703068?rel=author&#34;&gt;My Google+ Profile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>